Guide to the Robert Bernstein Papers TAM 726
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Bernstein Papers
1925-1936, 1956-2016
1995-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bernstein, Robert L., 1923-
TAM 726
13.9 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons, one oversize flat box, and one half manuscript box
2 audiocassettes
60 Gigabytes in one hard drive
8 sound discs (cd)
1 videodisc (dvd)
2.61 Megabytes in one document
Robert Bernstein (born 1923) is an American publisher and human rights advocate. He worked in publishing for over 45 years and was the president of Random House between 1966 and 1991. He is the founder of Human Rights Watch and served as the chair of the organization from its founding as Helsinki Watch in 1978 to 1998, and has served as Founding Chair Emeritus since 1998. The Robert Bernstein Papers document Bernstein's work in human rights and publishing; his autobiography, Speaking Freely: My Life in Publishing and Human Rights (2016); and other charitable organizations with which he is associated. Material in the collection documents both Bernstein's work in publishing and human rights, as well as the work of the organizations themselves. The collection dates between 1957 and 2016, with the bulk of the material dating between 1995 and 2010. Materials include correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, clippings, speeches, pamphlets, article and book drafts, oral history interviews, podcast episodes, print and born-digital photographs, a digital video recording, and scrapbooks.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Bernstein in 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.050.
Appraisal
Duplicate clippings and publications were deaccessioned.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series with each arranged in alphabetical order by name, topic, or format. The series are as follows:
Series I. Human Rights Watch Files, 1986-2016
Series II. Random House Files, 1925-1936, 1963-2001
Series III. Human Rights and Charitable Work Files, 1980-2014
Series IV. Biographical Material, 1956-2016
Biographical Note
Robert Bernstein (born 1923) is an American publisher and human rights advocate. He worked at Simon & Schuster from 1946 to 1956 and at Random House from 1956 to 1991, serving as the president of Random House between 1966 and 1991. He worked closely with Theodor Seuss Geisel (Dr. Seuss) on the Beginner Books division of Random House between 1959 and 1991.
After traveling to the Soviet Union a number of times between 1970 and 1973, and meeting with dissident authors Andrei Sakharov and Elena Bonner, he established the Fund for Free Expression in 1973 in order to promote the works of Sakharov, Bonner, and other dissident authors. He founded Helsinki Watch in 1978, which focused on the human rights section of the Helsinki Accords. Helsinki Watch led to other watch groups, which were all brought together under Human Rights Watch in 1988. Bernstein served as the chair between 1978 and 1998, and has served as Founding Chair Emeritus since 1998. He has been involved with several human rights organizations, including Advancing Human Rights and Human Rights in China. He served on the boards of several charitable organizations, including Legal Services for Children (later Partnership for Children's Rights), the Sigrid Rausing Trust, and Bard College's Institute for International Liberal Education and the Bard Prison Initiative. In 2016 he published his autobiography, Speaking Freely: My Life in Publishing and Human Rights.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Bernstein Papers document Bernstein's work in human rights and publishing; his autobiography, Speaking Freely: My Life in Publishing and Human Rights (2016); and other charitable organizations with which he was associated. The collection dates between 1925 and 2016, with the bulk of the material dating between 1995 and 2009. Materials include correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, clippings, speeches, pamphlets, article and book drafts, photographs, a digital video recording, oral history interviews, podcast episodes, and scrapbooks. Bernstein's work at Random House is documented through correspondence, contracts, interoffice memoranda, and oral history interviews with Bernstein. This material includes correspondence, contracts, and memoranda with and about Theodor Seuss Geisel's work for Random House as the head of Beginner Books. Bernstein's work with Human Rights Watch (HRW) is documented through correspondence, clippings, meeting agendas and minutes. Topics in these materials include human rights issues in Israel, Palestine, and China, with the bulk of the correspondence pertaining to HRW's and Bernstein's responses to events in the Middle East in particular. The collection contains material documenting Bernstein's relationship with other human rights and charitable organizations, including the Sigrid Rausing Trust, the Bard Prison Initiative, Legal Services for Children, Human Rights in China, and his relationships with Chinese dissidents Xu Wenli and Wei Jinsheng. His relationships with these organizations and people are documented through correspondence, meeting agenda, and print and born-digital photographs. Other material documenting the work of these people and organizations includes podcast episodes and a digital video recording. The collection also contains notes and background material for Speaking Freely and drafts of op-eds by Bernstein.
The collection contains overlap across the four series, with material pertaining to Bernstein's work with Random House, HRW, and other human rights organizations existing in Series IV. The materials filed under Series IV are a mix of material both unique and duplicative of that which exists in Series I through III.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Human rights monitoring.; Human rights -- Middle East.; Human rights -- China.; Human rights workers.; Autobiographies.; Memorandums.; Correspondence.; Publishers and publishing.; Human Rights Watch (Organization); Human Rights Watch (Organization). Middle East and North Africa Division; Human Rights in China (Organization)
- Series I. Human Rights Watch Files, 1986-2016; 2000-2009; 3.5 Linear Feet in four record cartons
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Bernstein's work with Human Rights Watch (HRW) through correspondence, clippings, meeting agendas and minutes, and publications of HRW and Human Rights Watch Middle East and North Africa. Material in this series dates between 1986 and 2016, with the bulk between 2000 and 2009. The bulk of the material focuses on HRW's coverage of Israel and Palestine, with correspondence between Bernstein, HRW staff, and people outside the organization analysing events in the region; op-eds by Bernstein on events in the region and relations within HRW; clippings; and publications by HRW.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by name, topic, or format.
  - Ackerman, Matthew, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Al-Aqsa, 2007-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Al Quds, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amnesty International, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anti-Semitism, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Apkon, Steve, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arab school books, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arafat, Suha, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Background and miscellany on Palestine-Israel relations, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bayefsky, Anne, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blum, Gabriella, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Center for Near East Policy, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Collaborators, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Court at the Hague, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - David Remnick on Egypt, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - European Union funding of terrorism, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fayyad, Salam, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The fence, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gaza/West Bank research, 2002-2014 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Goldstone, Richard, 2008-2011 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Genocide op-ed, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Habibi, Don, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Halbertal, Moshe, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hate speech, 2004-2015 (Box 1, Folder 28-37)
  - Herzog, Mike, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hessel, Stephane, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Human rights and laws of war, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Human rights research, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Human Rights Watch -- Bernstein, Robert - Joint Committee, 1993-2016 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  - Human Rights Watch -- Middle East/North Africa, 2004-2014 (Box 2, Folder 17-39, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Human Rights Watch -- Objectivity - World Bank, 1995-2012 (Box 3, Folder 5-13)
  - International Criminal Court, 2002-2014 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Israel, 1986-2013 (Box 3, Folder 16-29)
  - J Street, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Jenin, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Kahn, Joe, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lindsay, James G., 2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Middle East, 2006-2012 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick, 2002-2013 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - New Israel Fund, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Olson, Sheinberg, Peratis, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Op-eds, 2006-2013 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Palestinian Authority financial corruption, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - Palestinian organizations, 2000-2005 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Robinowitz, Stuart, 2008-2012 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
  - Roth, Ken, 2001-2005 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Sharansky's definition of anti-Semitism, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sheinberg, Sid, 2006-2011 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Telhami, Shibley, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Steinberg, Gerald, 2003-2010 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Stork, Joe, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Toameh, Khaled Abu, 2012-2015 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - United Nations on Israel, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - vanden Heuvel, William, 2009-2011 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - War, 1999-2010 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - White, Jeffrey, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Whitson, Sarah Leah, 2004-2011 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series II. Random House Files, 1925-1936, 1963-2001; 1963-1991; 2.3 Linear Feet in one record carton, one oversize flat box, and one half manuscript box; 2 sound discs (cd)
  This series documents Bernstein's career at Random House, with a focus on his relationship with Theodor Seuss Geisel (Dr. Seuss). Material in this series dates between 1925 and 2001 and includes correspondence, contracts, interoffice memoranda, a scrapbook of Dr. Seuss material, artwork, clippings, and oral history interviews with Bernstein regarding his time at Random House. The bulk of this material dates between 1963 and 1991 and pertains to Geisel's relationship with Random House, both as a writer and the president of the Beginners Books division. This material includes correspondence, interoffice memoranda, contracts, photographs, artwork by Geisel, and a scrapbook of material documenting his relationship with Random House. Correspondence and interoffice memoranda between Bernstein, Geisel, Helen Geisel, and Phyllis Jackson concerns renegotiations of Geisel's contract with Random House and his financial compensation from the company. Other material in this series includes transcripts and sound recordings of Bernstein's interviews as part of an oral history of Random House conducted in 2001 and letters from Alfred A. Knopf.
  - Beginner Books, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
  - Dr. Seuss Foundation, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Geisel, Theodor Seuss, 1959-2003 (Box 4, Folder 25-45, Box 13, Volume 1)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Modern Library and Random House 25th anniversary, 1925-1936, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Moscow Book Fair, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Organization Study of Random House, Inc., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - The Political Dr. Seuss, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Random House oral history project, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 14, Cd 7-8)
  - RCA agreements, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Stock purchases, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series III. Human Rights and Charitable Work Files, 1980-2014; 1993-2008; 5.7 Linear Feet in six record cartons and one half manuscript box; 6 sound discs (cd); 2.61 Megabytes in one document; 2 audiocassettes; 1 videodisc (dvd)
  This series documents Bernstein's human rights work outside of Human Rights Watch and his relationships with other charitable organizations. Material in this series dates between 1980 and 2014, with the bulk dating between 1993 and 2008. Bernstein's work with Human Rights in China (HRIC), the Sigrid Rausing Trust, Bard College's Institute for International Liberal Education and Bard Prison Initiative, and Legal Services for Children (later Partnership for Children's Rights), is documented by correspondence, meeting agenda and minutes, publications, clippings, podcast episodes, and a digital video recording. Included in this series is material related to Bernstein's work and personal relationships with Chinese dissidents Xu Wenli and Wei Jingsheng and his efforts to support their work in the United States. Filed under their names, drafts and published versions of print and born-digital writings by Xu and Wei may be found as well as digital photographs of Bernstein and Xu. Other material includes podcast episodes recorded by HRIC featuring interviews with participants of the 1989 Democracy Movement, a digital video recording produced by the Bard Prison Initiative about their program, subject files compiled by Bernstein on topics of interest to him, and speeches and op-eds written by Bernstein on human rights issues in general and in the Middle East in particular.
  - Advancing Human Rights, 2009-2011 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Army codes, 1988-2011 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Asymmetric warfare, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Bard College -- Helen Walter Bernstein Fund, 2002-2007 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bard College -- Institute for International Liberal Education, 1999-2011 (Box 5, Folder 9-22)
  - Bard College -- Bard Prison Initiative, 2002-2009 (Box 5, Folder 23-27, Box 14, Dvd 1)
  - Benshoof, Janet, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Blair, Dennis, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Brown University -- Watson Institute for International Studies, 2001-2008 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
  - Brown University -- Xu, Wenli, 2005-2007 (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
  - Carlisle, Michael, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 34, Box 14, Cassette 1-2)
  - Carr, Greg, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 2009-2011 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Committee for Economic Development, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Cotler, Irwin, 2002-2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Demers, Michele, 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Equality Now, 2005-2009 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fuller, Bonnie, 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Gold, Dore, 2009-2014 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Gregorian, Vartan, 2001-2004 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Haitian Education & Leadership Program, 2003-2010 (Box 6, Folder 10-12)
  - Havel, Václav, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Hellman-Hammet grants, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Hom, Sharon, 2005-2009 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Human Rights First, 2002-2007 (Box 6, Folder 16-19)
  - Human Rights in China, 1995-2013 (Box 6, Folder 20-34, Box 7, Folder 1-7, Box 14, Cd 1-6)
  - Interdisciplinary Center Herzliya, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - International Center for Transitional Justice, 2003-2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Julius, Anthony, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Kemp, Bruce, 2009-2011 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Kemp, Richard, 2014 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Kind, Friederike, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Legal Services for Children, 1998-2006 (Box 7, Folder 14-19)
  - Lewis, Bernard, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - MacArthur Foundation, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Moreno-Ocampo, Luis, 2003-2005 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - The New Press, 2003-2005 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - News of the Silenced, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - NGO Monitor, 2011-2013 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Nobel Prize winners, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Offit, Morris W., 2003 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Op-eds, 1990-2013 (Box 7, Folder 28-40, Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Open Society Institute, 2003-2005 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ovidiu Foundation, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Palestinian Media Watch, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Partnership for Children's Rights, 2006-2010 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Pincher, Chapman, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The Pollock-Krasner Foundation, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Prague Conference on Human Rights, 2004-2006 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Presidential Medal of Freedom, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Refugees, 2006-2010 (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
  - Sakharov, Andrei Dmitrivich and Elena Bonner, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Schiffrin, Andre, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Settlements, 2011 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Sharansky, Natan, 2004-2011 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Sigrid Rausing Trust, 2001-2006 (Box 8, Folder 19-34, Box 9, Folder 1-8)
  - Sinsheimer, Warren, 2001-2006 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Snepp, Frank W., 1980 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, 1986-2011 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Steiner, Nancy, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Tougaloo College, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - UN Watch, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2003-2010 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Various correspondence, 2001-2005 (Box 9, Folder 16-18)
  - Wang, Dan, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Wei, Jingsheng, 1994-2005 (Box 9, Folder 20-29, Box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - Women for Women International, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Workman Publishing, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - World Education, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - World Press Freedom Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - Wu, Harry, 2000-2004 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Xu, Jin, 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Xu, Wenli, 1993-2009 (Box 10, Folder 12-23, E-records Electronic records, Object TA_WAM_726_2)
  - Yemini, Ben Dror, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 24)
- Series IV. Biographical Material, 1956-2016; 1994-2007; 3 Linear Feet in two record cartons and one oversize flat box
  This series contains materials collected by Bernstein throughout his career and while writing his autobiography, Speaking Freely: My Life in Publishing and Human Rights. Material in this series dates between 1956 and 2016, with the bulk between 1994 and 2007. Material includes clippings about Bernstein regarding his work in publishing and human rights, correspondence, notes and drafts of op-eds written by Bernstein, drafts and reviews of Speaking Freely, speeches given by and about Bernstein, and awards conferred upon Bernstein. There is some duplication of material that can be found in Series I, II, and III. This series contains biographies of Bernstein for organizational publications and event programs, different versions of Bernstein's curriculum vitae, and scrapbooks compiled by Bernstein. The scrapbooks document Bernstein's career in publishing and human rights, and include compilations of material listed above, including clippings, speeches, and awards.
  - Awards and speeches, 1976-2003 (Box 10, Folder 25-31)
  - Biographies, 1976-2001 (Box 10, Folder 32-33)
  - Bonner, Elena, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1962-2007 (Box 10, Folder 35, Box 11, Folder 1-10, Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Colbert, Claudette, 1973-1996 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1956-2013 (Box 11, Folder 12-19)
  - Curricula vitae, 1989-1998 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Everett, Edith, 2008 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Interview, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Johnson, Anne, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Klopfer, Donald S., 1987 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Op-eds, 2008-2012 (Box 11, Folder 25-26)
  - Photograph, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbooks, 1950-2003 (Box 11, Folder 28-34)
  - Speaking Freely: My Life in Publishing and Human Rights, 1997-2016 (Box 11, Folder 35-42, Box 12, Folder 1-14)
  - Yale Law inaugural, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 15)